there are two different price action
trading Concepts that when combined
create one of my personal favorite entry
models and these Concepts actually build
up the backbone of the majority of my
trading strategy they are liquidity and
Market structure in this class I want to
give you a deep understanding of both
and share with you an entry model and a
trading system that you can start to
apply to make some good trades and make
some profits so with that said and done
let's get into the learning Market
Structure Theory suggests that markets
move in three phases we have uptrends we
we have downtrends and we have
consolidation now an uptrend is simply a
phase where a market is continually
moving to the upside and through an
uptrend we only want to buy a market a
downtrend is the opposite where a market
is continually moving to the downside
and through these markets we only want
to sell now a consolidation is generally
where we just move sideways there's no
real trading opportunities most of the
time inside of consolidation ranges so
we pretty much want to eliminate this
and just focus on uptrends and
downtrends to determine whether a market
is in an uptrend or a downtrend we want
to look at the highs and the lows in
price so we can see in the uptrend we
form higher highs and higher lows a
market that is forming new highs and
lows higher than the previous highs and
lows is an uptrend okay we can see the
Market's clearly moving up but we Define
that by the fact that the market is
continuing to push past these previous
highs right so this here is what we call
a break of structure it's this push
upwards past the higher high high this
as well is a break of structure and the
actual break of structure we talk about
is taking place at these points because
we get these breaks in structure that
continue pushing the market higher this
is indeed an uptrend a downtrend is
pretty much the same but flipped upside
down so in a downtrend we are forming
lower lows and lower highs and what that
simply means is every low and every high
that forms in the market is lower than
the previous once again we indicate the
continuation of a downtrend with these
breaks of structure which is when the
market pushes past a previous low the
next thing you need to know is that a
trending movement is made up of two main
parts we have impulsive movements and we
have corrective movements so impulses
and Corrections now an Impulse is a prot
trend movement it's the movement that
breaks the structure so in an uptrend
after we form a higher high a corrective
move will pull down to form a higher low
and then the impulsive move is defined
by the movement that breaks through the
previous higher high forming a new
higher high so those are the impulsive
moves the prot trend larger movements
that break structure corrective moves
are just pullbacks that don't really
break any significant structure but they
allow the formation of new higher lows
to keep us understanding which way the
market is going now eventually Trends
come to an end we can Define when
they're coming to an end by looking at
the higher lows so here we have this
impulsive bullish Trend we have an
uptrend in this market we only want to
buy but what happens if the market comes
down and breaks through this low like
this well now we would get a new
impulsive move this movement here but
this would be a bearish impulse the
reason we know this is an Impulse is
because it's broken through the previous
higher low which breaks this higher high
higher low formation and breaks the
uptrend so from this point onwards we
would instead now be expecting the
market to make a lower high and then a
new lower low and then new lower highs
and lower lows to continue this Market
in downtrending fashion where we
basically shift from this bullish Trend
into a bearish one so here is a view of
that full piece of trending structure we
have bullish impulses and Corrections
where the market is continually breaking
through new higher highs and making new
structural higher highs and lows then we
have that break which is a bearish
impulse that pushes past the higher low
forming a lower low then we get a
pullback corrective move forming a lower
high then we break more structure into
new lower lows and lower highs and so on
so that is how a trend works and it
pretty much runs like this all of the
time the majority of the time in the
market the Market's going to be trending
one way or the other except for of
course those consolidation moves that we
said we don't want to trade now let's
talk about liquidity liquidity refers to
orders or money now markets move due to
orders and money and transactions taking
place and passing hands in the market
now to understand liquidity we just want
to think about where people are
generally buying and selling from so if
we know in this trending movement here
we have a low a swing low and we have a
s swing high and these have formed in
the market already we know there's going
to be some level of buyers down here we
know there's going to be some level of
sellers at the high okay people trade
different strategies generally once the
markets make highs and lows whether it's
based on supply and demand support and
resistance or any other concept people
will be buying above lows selling above
highs now these Traders generally follow
simple advice the majority of them do
any Trader who buys at a swing low or
just after a swing low is formed will
generally have stop- losses underneath
the low anyone who sells will generally
have stop losses just above the high
it's rare that you buy somewhere in a
trend and then just put your stop loss
in that trending movement as well
generally you want to clear highs and
lows it's common education yes it works
but it also creates a lot of liquidity
so these areas that we've just marked
become liquidity okay there's liquidity
here there's liquidity here now why is
that well that is because there's a
significant number of orders at either
of these levels and markets react to
orders the reason markets move is
because of injections of buying orders
and selling orders now if we know that
multiple Buys have been taking place
here potentially thousands by different
Traders well now we know there's a
collection of thousands of different
orders waiting here in the form of stop
losses as well as this we have breakout
traders who would have sell stop orders
here thinking if the market comes and
breaks through this low I want to be
triggered into a sell to take the market
lower so we have stop losses and we have
sell stop orders under here in the
thousands which creates liquidity we
have the same up here at the top but we
have stop losses for Sellers and then we
have buy stops as well so there's a
whole lot of orders transactions
awaiting at the highs and the lows now
because we know that markets react to
orders where is the market most likely
to react now somewhere randomly in the
middle of this area well probably not
it's more likely to see significant
reactions once highs or lows have been
taken because that is where the orders
are going to be that could potentially
Drive the new movements in the market so
we may hit the swing high and then see a
significant sell lower hit the swing low
see a significant move higher that is
the kind of premise of liquidity forming
above swing highs and swing lows it's
simply the market reacting to areas
where the majority of the orders are
situated okay now as we discussed there
are ways to understand where this is
likely to take place so looking over
here now we have a market that's formed
a bearish impulse then we have two highs
which are level with one another and we
have two almost three lows which are
level with one another now from a
support and resistance approach which
the majority of Traders or beginners are
actually looking at we have a support
and a resistance okay what are Traders
looking to do at support and resistance
well generally what we've just discussed
right Traders want to buy Above support
so there will be buy orders placed here
hoping the market moves higher and
Traders want to sell below resistance so
we know from this there are going to be
stop losses down here there are going to
be stop losses up here and we also get
those sell stops and buy stops as we
discussed okay so up here we have stop
losses from buyers but we also have buy
stops from breakout traders who are
looking for a new high to form down here
we have the stop losses and the sell
stops from Traders looking for the
opposite we have these stop- losses for
buyers but we also have sell stops for
breakout traders who are expecting to
see a kind of break retest scenario in
the market and remember these are very
very common Concepts to trade sometimes
you get stuck in the bubble of kind of
price action Concepts on YouTube but
you'd be underestimating how many people
around the world are trading with
support resistance and these basic
similar Concepts where is the liquidity
then is it sitting in the middle of this
slow moving range no it's at the highs
and the lows it's above here it's below
here this is where the liquidity is this
is where those major reactions are
likely to take place so what we would be
looking for as Traders is for the low to
go and then to look for some opportunity
to trade higher or for the market to
trade Above This high and then this is
where we would look for opportunities to
trade lower so when we understand the
liquidity here what we actually do is
get two beneficial things we get
potential targets at these highs and
lows because if we know that the market
is likely to attack these highs and lows
well then we can find opportunity to
trade towards those levels for example
if the market swept this low well now if
we saw a reaction a reversal in the
price we could look for a long
opportunity back up towards this High
because we know it's likely the Market's
going to come and attack this liquidity
as well and if the structure then agrees
with us the structure being what we've
just discussed and don't worry we'll
elaborate on this more then we have good
means for getting into a position and
tackling the other points of liquidity
now as you can imagine the other thing
it's good for is entries as I've just
highlighted if the market was to come
all the way up here and we know there's
more liquidity down here we can use this
area now that it's been swept to find an
opportunity to sell down so we would
actually look for that structural change
so just like this a market that's
changing from higher highs and higher
lows into lower lows and lower highs we
could sell there and we could look to
tackle the next point of liquidity and
probably now you can see how we're
starting to formulate a trading setup so
this is the entry model that I want to
show you in this video using structure
and liquidity together let me break it
down what we've got is a bearish market
we have bearish impulses and then we
have the small corrective moves as
discussed now in a bearish market we are
seeing these lower lows and lower highs
form we then want to identify points of
liquidity in the form of those equal
highs as we just discussed so where we
saw the resistance level we know there's
stop losses and buy stops Above This
level that's what we want to identify
now sometimes this is going to formulate
inside of a bearish movement and when
you see this this becomes a very high
probability setup so we are looking for
a market that is bearish forming a
notable trend of lower lows and lower
highs then we want to identify that
liquidity in the form of equal highs or
a resistance and then once the market
breaks those equal highs or break breaks
that resistance level comes into the
area where the liquidity is we will use
a final tip called supply and demand to
find our entry now this Zone here is a
supply zone so it is basically a area
just before a large bearish impulsive
movement down and the concept is once
the market comes into this level again
we would then look to sell so after we
come up into it we see this as a high
probability area to sell from because
we've seen significant selling taking
place from this level before which shows
that this is a level that sellers accept
as a premium price to sell from it's a
good level to sell from the market gets
back here it's seen as a good premium to
sell from again so just to recap this
one more time before I show you an
actual example we are looking for a
bearish trend we want to make sure the
market is forming notable lower lows and
lower highs when it does we are then
looking for the formation of some equal
highs some resistance then once that
resistance is taken we are looking to
sell using that final tip the supply
Zone that we just discussed okay now
this can work on any time frame and
don't worry if this is a little bit
confusing now you will see it in real
markets in just one moment now one final
question you might have about this entry
model is how is this not a break of
structure right as we said when the
market breaks through a previous high or
low this should be seen as a break of
structure so why are we now looking to
sell even though we've had what we could
call a break of structure why don't we
look instead for a continuation into new
buys well the reason for that is because
of how the market re reacts to liquidity
right if this wasn't equal highs if this
wasn't a resistance and this didn't have
a significant amount of liquidity above
it then we would indeed see this break
as a breaking structure but because it's
equal highs because the resistance is
still here the stop loss is the buy
stops all of this stuff is here and the
remainder of this bearish trend is still
intact then it remains possible and
highly likely that this will be a false
break of structure where instead of
breaking and then continuing we break
just to sweep liquidity o the equal
highs so if there wasn't any equal highs
here and the market looked like this
instead then yes we would look to buy
but because we have that resistance
because we have those equal highs it
becomes high probability to sell so when
you're trying to work out whether it's a
Breakin structure or a sweep of
liquidity just consider that do we have
a point of significant liquidity like
equal highs or resistance level if we do
then it's likely the break will actually
fail and actually just sweep liquidity
before continuing the selloff now let's
get to an example of this on the chart
take a look at this price structure here
we have a large upward move forming a
higher high pull back to form a higher
low a push up to form a new higher high
then we have a higher low a higher high
and then we have this break-in structure
here which brings us into lower lows
Okay so we've just made that shift from
bullish into bearish right we've seen
this structure shifting down now we have
a bearish impulse this becomes a bearish
trend or bearish market so this is our
high this is is our low the market then
comes back and forms this lower high
before coming down to make this lower
low now the reason that we don't really
want to consider this intermediate
structure is because this is what we
call the consolidation that we looked at
right we said there's three phases
consolidations we don't really want to
trade but we can see that this area here
the market didn't really make any
movements other than sideways it's only
when we broke through into the next low
at this level here that we continued
with the bearish trend
so it's kind of just a pause in the
trend where the market does nothing but
go sideways so at this point we have a
bearish trend we've got the impulses
that we want to see we've got the
smaller Corrections and then we've got
this messy consolidation now what forms
during a consolidation well
consolidation areas is where we are
going to get these equal highs that we
just discussed so here we can see one
two pushes up and then a little bit
lower down we've got a bunch of other
pushes as well we could pretty safely
say that this area here as a
or if we wanted to get really refined it
would be this area that I've just marked
out is seen as a resistance in price so
there are going to be sellers somewhere
within this range there will be breakout
Traders at this point now looking for a
break Above This high so traders who are
expecting if this happens their buy
stops will trigger them into buys for a
break retest continuation and there will
also be sellers taking place anywhere
inside of this range could be here could
be even where we are now could have been
previous at this resistance retest
whatever but these sellers are going to
generally in Mass at least a lot of them
as a generalization have stop losses
above these equal highs and above this
high so this creates an area where there
is a significant amount of liquidity
orders or transactions which means if
the market reaches back into this point
such as a sweep above the swing High we
would then look for a continuation lower
that's what we would expect to see okay
if we then consider the final thing we
discussed which was a supply Zone I said
a supply Zone was a consolidation area
before a large downward move now this
candle here is a huge Wick where we
opened and closed at the same level so
this is what we consider as our
consolidation area we are looking for
what I call the last candle before the
impulse this is the last candle before
the bearish impulse that broke structure
so this here that large candle that
large bearish candle is our supply Zone
okay so now we've got a few things let
me annotate we've got our low which
indicates a new bearish trend we we've
got our supply Zone which indicates a
solid level to sell from Once the market
reacts to it once again because it was
seen as a premium to sell from before
and we've got uh equal High liquidity
just above the consolidation which is
going to be pretty much this level here
right we can draw this out it is
relative equal Highs at this time so
we're missing it by about one pip but we
can clearly see this is a resistance
level uh they don't have to be to the
PIP direct equal high stone but they
have to be very very very close to the
point that you know when we take a look
at this you can see how refined and how
close together these levels truly are so
with what we can see here on the chart
let me map out the entry model once
again that we just discussed so we have
our bearish Trend we have the formation
of equal highs within that bearish Trend
we then sweep above the equal highs and
then sell back below so the equal highs
just here the supply Zone just here and
this has to be taking place in a bearish
trend right so we see bearish so we see
bearish impulses equal highs sell from
Supply once equal highs have been swept
bearish impulse equal highs sell from
so how do we approach this then for an
actual trade position well what we're
now looking for as Traders if you
haven't already guessed it is for the
market to sweep equal highs trade into
Supply and then we will be looking to
sell the market down from there so at
this point we can go ahead and place an
order so our sell limit would be at this
level here the best way to get these
trades it's going to be a sell limit
because a sell limit just triggers you
in once the market reaches that level
you get triggered into a sell and then
if the market reverses as we expect it
to you will then profit for the stop
loss I like to keep it above the high
right we can put it above the supply
Zone that would be fine simply because
we're so close to the high here I'd
actually put it just above the high just
in case the market decides to Wick or
anything that is going to make your
trade a little bit safer if you just
always clear the highs you don't need to
kind of push your luck for the biggest
possible risk reward that's going to be
fine now targets wise what we can do
because we are now in a bearish trend is
just look for open areas below for
targets I like to use once again either
points of liquidity so swing lows or
just areas of demand which would be
basically the opposite of a supply Zone
a consolidation before a large upward
move so if we go take a look at the
bottom of this Movement we have here our
area of consolidation before this large
upward move we could use this as a
Target okay that is our demand Zone
trade would look like this and that
would be the entry model pretty much
prepped out so this would be a solid
trade we now have this price range and
this demand that we can trade through so
what we would do at this point is simply
place a solit order and then allow the
market to run through what we're looking
for is for the market to trade into the
area of Supply as we've just seen happen
and then sell off from there towards
wherever our Target may be in this new
bearish trend now you would have been
safe with your stop above the Zone we
went a little bit higher and put it
above the high which is completely fine
this would be 4.6 9% return for every 1%
risked and it followed that entry model
perfectly we have bearish impulses equal
highs sweep equal highs sell from Supply
and Target further down in the trend and
by the way just to highlight it yes you
can trade this the other way if we were
in a bearish trend that shifted into a
bullish Trend we could actually trade
this using equal lows and demand it
works exactly the same both ways doesn't
matter if you're buying or selling you
just need to be following the correct
Trend so if we begin a new uptrend Trend
you can use equal lows and demand zones
to buy instead of sell using the exact
same entry model so that is a simplistic
entry model that you can use to start
putting liquidity and Market structure
together into action in the markets to
make profits from your trading what you
should do next is go to the top Link in
the description of this video and sign
up to my completely free system building
course I show you how to turn this into
a trading strategy then how to back test
it Journal it and validate it so you can
trade it live with an understanding of
the win Ates and other important metrics
if you don't have a system you won't win
it trading so take advantage of it it's
completely free and with that said and
done I'll see you in the next video